<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <style>
            body {
            font-family: "Georgia", Times, serif;
            background-color: #faf0e6;
            color: #6F4E37;
            }
            
            h1 {
            text-align: center;
            font-size:60px;}
            
            h2 {
            font-size:40px;}
             
            h3 {
            font-size:30px;}
            
            h4 {
            font-size:25px;}

            h5 {
            text-align: center;
            font-size:30px;}
         
            
           #photo1 {  width: 400px; 
                      height: 500px }
                      
            #photo2 {  width: 400px; 
                      height: 500px }
                      
            #photo3 {  width: 400px; 
                      height: 500px }
                      
             #photo4 {  width: 400px; 
                      height: 500px }

              #photo5 {  width: 400px; 
                      height: 500px }
                      
            #t1right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t2right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t3right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t4right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t5right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t6right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t7right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t8right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            
            #t9right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t10right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t11right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t12right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t13right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t14right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t15right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t16right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t17right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t18right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t19right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t20right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t21right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t22right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t23right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t24right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t25right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t26right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #t27right {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr1 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr2 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr3 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr4 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr5 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr6 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr7 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            #leftptr8 {
            text-align:right;}
            
            body {  
            margin-right: 100px;
            margin-left: 100px;  }
            
            </style>
        
        
    </head>
    <body>
        <h1><u>Collection Title</u></h1>
        <h2>Introduction</h2>
        
        <div>
        <h5>Charles Starkweather to J. M. Reinhardt Letter, 27 January 1959</h5>
        <img src="letter_jan27_page1.jpg" id="photo1"/>
        <img src="letter_jan27_page2.jpg" id="photo2"/>
        <div>
            INSPECTED JAN 29 1959 NEBRASKA STATE PENITENTIARY<br></br>
        <br></br>
      Charles Starkweather<br></br>
      
      Box 111 – 20396<br></br>
      Lincoln, Nebr.<br></br>
      
      Jan. 27, 1959
        <br></br>
        <br></br>
      <div class="opening_salutation">Dear Mr. Reinhardt:</div>
      
      
      
      <p>I appreciate the fact that you wanted to edit my life story for me. but i can not
         agree to the way in which your going about it. so to keep from having feelings between
         us come to a disliking point in the near future. i would please like to have all of
         my manuscript return and i'm sorry if you have spent to much time on it, and if is
         cost you any trouble, and i assure you the money you have invested up to date, <b>well [sic] be paid to you in full.</b></p>
      
      <p>Please return immediately to me at the Nebraska State Penitentiary <b>all containing parts</b> of the <b>original,</b> and <b>copies</b> of the following chapters – 1, <b>2</b> and –<b>3</b> of my manuscript. <b>Also,</b> in your possession, you have three, <b>(3)</b> large pictures, plus six, <b>(6)</b> small pictures, which are hand drawn by myself, and i wish those nine <b>(9) in all.</b> pictures are also return immediately along with the manuscript.</p>
      
      <p>I'm not going to sell my story to no body, i'm a little disgusted over the headaches
         it's caused, but i hope to remain writing on it, and maybe we'll be able to get together
         on it later one, <b>but not at this time.</b></p>
      
      
      <p>Please return my manuscript, and pictures. at once, i'm impatiently waiting for their
         return, and as you well know my time is very limited.</p>
      
      <div class="closing_salutation">
      Thank you—<br></br>
      Yours truely[sic]<br></br>
      Charles Starkweather
      </div>
      </div>


        </div>

        <div>
        <h5>Charles Starkweather to J. M. Reinhardt Letter, 27 April 1959</h5>
        <img src="letter_apr27_page1.jpg" id="photo3"/>
        <img src="letter_apr27_page2.jpg" id="photo4"/>
<div>
            Charles Starkweather<br></br>
      
      Box 111 – #20396<br></br>
      Lincoln, Nebraska<br></br>
      
      April 27, 1959
      <br></br>
      <br></br>
      <div class="opening_salutation">Dear Mr. Reinhardt:</div>
      
      
      
      <p>I appreciate the fact that you have paid attention to my family and myself in the
         past but that does not give you an excuse for not returning my manuscript.</p>
      
      <p>On Feb. 7, 1959 you made a <FONT COLOR="#ff0000">RELEASE</FONT> with my family releasing you from any previous agreements, also that release specified
         very clearly that you had no further interest or jurisdiction containing to that of
         my three chapters of my manuscripts which is now in your possession. You have informed
         us perviously [sic] that you had two typed, word for word copies made which should
         be sufficient to you, and which i nor the family have not disapprove of, but the release
         also clearly specified that you have no more need for my manuscript, and my family
         and i can not under–stand why you well[sic] not return the original script as you
         promised to do so at the close of the "Parade Magazin" publication on March 15, 1959.
         I wrote you a letter a few weeks before the Parade made these publication, stating
         that my desire was to have the manuscript return. And in reply, you told my family
         that you didn't have to return it until <FONT COLOR="#ff0000">(</FONT>30 days.<FONT COLOR="#ff0000">)</FONT>. i assure you Mr. Reinhardt them 30 days have lapsed quite abit. I have quite abit
         of doubt in your character at this time. You have insisted to my family and myself
         several times that you're an honorable, trustworthy and a true–to–your–word person,
         but in my mind, there's doubt, but i insist on proof that you are what you say you
         are by the immediate return of my entire three chapters of my manuscript to me at
         this Nebraska State Penitentiary.</p>
      
      <div class="closing_salutation">Respectfully yours<br></br>
      Charles Starkweather
      </div>
      
     <br></br>
      <div class="reinhardt_note">I went to see Charles and explained that the m.s. was my copied-phototake - and would
      be returned to him (fo/a) &amp; was returned promptly(?)</div>
</div>
        </div>

    </body>
</html>
